Autism stems from differences in biology that have an influence
on brain development.
Autism is a lifelong condition. That doesn't mean that children
can't make significant improvements in their language and social abilities
over time. They can, just like all children. But children
don't just grow out of autism.
Autism can affect a person's ability to understand subtle emotional
cues, such as tone of language or body language. But
when emotions are communicated more directly, there's a wealth of
evidence showing that children and adults on the spectrum are
even more likely to feel empathy for others.
Social interaction difficulties and anxiety can sometimes mean that making
friends is a struggle.
But this should never be confused with a lack of
desire to have friendships. The vast majority of children and
adults on the spectrum do like to socialise, and sometimes
that just means socialising in a different way.
It is true that around 10% of autistic people have
skills such as maths or drawing that are of extraordinary
ability, but this is really just a small proportion of
the full numbers of individuals diagnosed with autism. It's best
to look past this caricature and see the extraordinary human
that lies beyond the diagnosis.
100%, categorically, no. There have been literally thousands of studies
in this area, and all of them have found no
association between vaccinations and autism.
The assumption that people on the spectrum don't have a
sense of humour is Absolutely false. Probably the funniest conversations
I've ever had have been with autistic kids and adults,
and they absolutely run rings around me in telling jokes.
Don't be fooled by the news stories that you may
see. There is no evidence that individuals on the spectrum
are more violent than the rest of the population. None.
Many people on the spectrum are in wonderful, loving romantic
relationships. Just like the rest of the community, not every
person on the spectrum chooses to be in a romantic
relationship, but that is not the same as not being
capable of doing so.
Many people on the spectrum have intellectual disabilities, and also
many do not. Just because someone may have communication difficulties
doesn't mean that they also have intellectual disabilities. What it
means is that we have to assess intelligence in a
different way, a way that doesn't rely so heavy on
communication skills.
Not every child will be great at maths. Not every
child will repeat back words. Not every child will have
difficulty speaking, and not every child will have hand mannerisms.
Every child and adult on the autism spectrum is different.
Full of their own unique talents, personalities, and yes, challenges.
The label autism doesn't mean one thing. What it is
is a gateway to understanding a whole new way of
thinking about the world, and those children and adults are
to be cherished for that fact.